Preliminary Inventory to the William H. Friedland Collection, 1929-1967
Hoover Institution Archives
William H. Friedland Collection,
1929-1967
69042
Friedland, William H., collector.
10 manuscript boxes, 3 envelopes, 5 microfilm reels. (4.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Reports, articles, minutes of meetings, and clippings, relating to Tanzanian trade-unions.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
Access Points
Trade-unions--Tanzania.; Africa.; Tanzania.
Container List
General
- I. Newspaper clippings, primarily from Tanganyika Standard, 1959-1964
  - Cooperatives, 1962-1964. (Box 1)
  - Crime, 1959-1963.
  - Economics & miscellaneous, 1959-1962.
  - Economics, 1959-1963.
  - Education, 1960-1964.
  - Foreign affairs, 1961-1963.
  - Independence Day (Dec. 9, 1961).
  - Miscellaneous, 1960-1964.
  - OAU (Organization for African Unity), 1967.
  - African socialism, 1962-64.
  - Political news (TANU), Sept. 1959 - Aug. 1960. (Box 2)
  - Political news (TANU), Aug. 1960 - Apr. 1961.
  - Political news (TANU), Apr. 1961 - Aug. 1961.
  - Political news (TANU), Aug. 1961 - Nov. 1961.
  - Political news (TANU), Jan. 1962 - June 1962.
  - Political news (TANU), July 1962.
  - Political news (TANU), Aug. - Dec. 1962. (Box 3)
  - Political news (TANU), Jan 1963.
  - Political news (TANU), Feb. - Apr. 1964.
  - Political news (TANU), May - Aug. 1964.
  - Postal Union (TAPU), 1960 - 1963.
  - Self-help and Cooperation
    - Uganda (from Uganda Argus, 1967)
    - Kenya (East African Standard, 1967).
  - TANU Youth League, 1962-1964.
  - Trade Unions, Jan. - June 1962.
  - Trade Unions, July - Dec. 1962.
  - Trade Unions, Jan. - June 1963.
  - Trade Unions, July - Dec. 1963.
  - "Week's Personality," 1960-1963.
  - Zanzibar, 1961-1963.
  - "Summary of Vernacular Press," prep. by Tanganyika Information Service, July 26, 1960 - June 18, 1962. (Box 4)
- II. Minutes of General Council and of Annual Conferences of Tanganyika Federation of Labor, 1950-1960
  - TFL General Council meeting, Moshi, Mar. 28-31, 1956. (Box 5)
  - TFL Annual Conference, Hindu Mandal Dar-es-Salaam, Oct. 5-7, 1956.
  - TFL General Council meeting, Tanga, July 4-6, 1957.
  - TFL Summary of resolutions passed at General Conference, Nov. 27-28, 1957.
  - TFL General Council meeting, June 25-26, 1958.
  - TFL Annual Conference, Dar-es-Salaam, Nov. 23-26, 1958.
  - TFL General Council meeting, Dodoma, Apr. 18-20, 1959.
  - TFL Conference working session, Dec. 5, 1959.
  - TFL General Council meeting, Aug. 27-28, 1960
  - TFL Minutes of Emergency Executive Committee Meetings, 1958-1960. (Box 6)
  - TFL Trade Councils general reports, 1960, 1961, 1962.
  - Tanganyika Standard summaries, a partial chronology of major trade union events in Tanganyika, 1929 to mid-1959, (handwritten notes with typed copy).
  - Chronological outline of TFL meetings, Aug. 1960 - Dec. 1964, (handwritten).
  - Extract from Diary, July 27, 1960, re Morogero branch of Postal Workers Union.
  - "A Description of Minimum Wages," and "Trade Unions and Their Meaning," booklets in Swahili by TFL president Rashidi M. Kawawa, in English translations.
- III. Various Files - Subjects designated
  - Notes and outlines on Tanganyika Trade Union History. (Box 7)
  - "The History of the Founding of TFL, 1955-1962," and "The Formation of NUTA, 1964," by A.C.A. Tandau., (Original handwritten copy & process. copy)
  - Report on Ministry of Labour's proposal to integrate with TFL.
  - TFL Leadership schedules.
  - ICFTU African Labour College: information, outlines and examinations.
  - Lists and reports of "Early interviews, 1959-1960."
  - Questionnaire outline, Ibadan, Nigeria, with answers, Sept. 23, 1960.
- IV. Reports and Minutes of various Trade Unions in Tanganyika (with some correspondence)
  - Commercial and Industrial Workers' Union, MS copy/copies of Rules (Constitution) of Tanganyika. (Box 8)
  - Transcript of DMT Negotiations (no date).
  - Local Government Workers' Union.
  - Plantation Workers' Union.
  - Postal Workers' Union.
  - Public Employees' Union.
  - Railway Workers' Union.
  - Transportation General Workers' Union.
  - Various other unions.
  - Brief sketch of TANU (political party).
  - "The Recognition of African Trade Unions," by Julius Lewin, from Race Relations, v. 9:4, 1942 (039), (reprint).
  - "Trade Unions and Industrial Relations in Australian New Guinea," by J. R. Kerr, from Journal of Industrial Relations, v. 3:1, Apr. 1961 (098), (photo copy).
  - "Memoranda of agreements between Tanganyika Breweries Ltd. and Transport and General Workers' Union, Aug. 16, 1962" (098), (photo copy).
  - "Counterproposal by Tanganyika Plantation Workers' Union, e.g., Tanganyika Sisal Growers' Association" (098), (photo copy).
  - "Memorandum of Agreement between the Tanganyika Sisal Growers' Association and Tanganyika Plantation Workers' Union." (098), (photo copy).
  - "Constitution of the Tanganyika Plantation Workers' Union" (1963) (098), (photo copy).
  - 3 reprints from newspapers on TFL and party politics, dated Aug. 16 and Aug. 20, 1959.
  - "Labour Songs," pamphlet, Ibadan (Nigeria) (036).
  - "In the heart of Mother Africa" (pamphlet) ICFTU (059).
  - TFL posters in Swahili (English translation noted) (016).
  - German Trade Union Federation Organizational Chart (034).
- V. Various Files - Subjects Designated
  - L&SCo.EA (Landing & Shipping Co. of East Africa), terms of employment. (001) (Box 9)
  - EAR&H (East African Railways & Harbors), staff consultation. (002)
  - EAR&H, opportunities for employment. (003)
  - Agreement between Tea Growers' Association & Plantation Workers Union. (004)
  - Collective bargaining in plantation industries in T.T. (005)
  - Jack Report on methods of determining wages. (006)
  - Comments by Tanganyika Federation of Labor on Jack Report. (007)
  - Materials from Plantation Workers' Conference [in Swahili], October 17, 1959. (008)
  - cc. of Guillebaud memo to TSGA (Tanganyika Sisal Growers Association) in preparations for meeting union. (009)
  - Constitution of Sisal & Plantation Workers' Union. (010)
  - Materials from TACTU (Tanganyika African Catholic Teachers Union) Conference. Agenda. Report of General Secretary. (011A, 011B)
  - Minutes of meetings of CJC (Central Joint Council) of sisal industry. (012A, 012G)
  - Materials from 5th Conference of TFL 1959 (Dec.) [in Swahili and English] (A-1) (013)
  - "Trade Union News" of TFL. (014)
  - Constitutions of various trade unions in T.T. (015)
  - Two organization posters of TFL. (016)
  - Bulletin of the ICFTU Area Committee [removed Apr. 1964]. (017)
  - Collective Agreements (018)
    - T&GWU (Transport & General Workers' Union) & Tanna Brothers, Tabora.
    - Mine Workers & Williamson's.
    - [no heading]
    - TSGA (Tanganyika Sisal Growers Association) and PWU (Plantation Workers' Union).
    - Constitution of the CJC of the sisal industry.
    - Wage agreement of April 1960 in sisal industry.
  - Jerraud, "Hints on the Care and Management of African Labour," 1937. (019)
  - Arnautoglu Community Centre, Annual Report, 1958.
  - Materials prepared by Public Relations Dept., Tanganyika Gov't. (021)
  - Constitution of Tanganyika Workers' Education Association. (022)
  - TALGWU (Tanganyika African Local Government Workers' Union) Annual Conference - Dodoma, June 1960 - Materials.
    - A - Agenda - original.
    - B - Agenda - second agenda - in translation.
    - C - List of branches.
    - D - President's speech.
    - E - General Secretary's Report.
    - F - Short history of the Union.
    - G - General Treasurer's Report.
    - H - Monthly remittances from branches to HQ in 1959.
    - I - Membership of union, paid up, unpaid, etc., by branches, 1959.
  - Materials from TAPU (Tanganyika African Postal Union) Conference.
    - Agenda.
    - Presidential Address.
    - General Secretary's Address.
    - Standing Orders of the Conference.
    - Report of the General Secretary.
    - Report of the General Treasurer.
    - Report on the dispute with the Postal Administration.
    - Summary in strike income and expenditure.
    - Provisional financial estimates for 1960.
  - Materials relating to TRAU (Tanganyika Railroad African Union) Conference.
    - Invitation of opening session.
    - Program of
    - Agenda.
    - Presidential Address.
    - General Secretary's Report.
    - General Treasurer's Report.
    - Income and expenditures 1959.
    - Letter to the Governor.
  - T & GWU Annual Conference materials. (026) (Box 10)
  - TUPE Conference materials. (027)
  - Expenditure and consumption of African labour in Dar-es-Salaam (Ohanga Report). (028)
  - Instructors Handbook for Trade Union Leadership Training. Aug. - Sep. 1960. (028A)
  - Zanzibar & Pemba Federation of Labor Draft Constitution. (031)
  - Public Services International Report on Africa (Mar. 19-20, 1959). (077)
  - Report on plantations situation in the British Cameroons, Dec. 29, 1957-1958 (Tom Bavin report). (087)
  - ICFTU (International Confederation of Free Trade Unions), Bibliography. (88)
  - ICFTU (International Confederation of Free Trade Unions), Bibliography. African Regional Conference, Accra, Jan. 1957 (089)
  - ICFTU Agenda of African Regional Conference, Jan. 14-19, 1957. (090)
  - ICFTU, preparatory committee for African Regional Conference, Geneva, June 7, 1956. (091)
  - Report on Mauritius Plantations Survey, Dec. 5-8, 1957. (092)
  - Julius Lewin, "The Struggle for Law in South Africa," reprint from Political Quarterly (London), April 1956. (093)
  - Ghana Trades Union Congress, General Statement outlining Congress' stand on behalf of workers - press communiqué. (094)
  - Ghana Trades Union Congress, educational classes curriculum, Sept. - Dec. 1960. (095)
  - National Union of Tanganyika workers, list of officers.
  - Sample "agreement" form for Tanganyika Plantation Workers' Union.
  - TFL Institute programme, Feb. 1962.
  - TFL Seminar programme, July 7-13, 1962.
  - TFL Seminar programme, Aug. 10-24, 1963.
  - TFL Education & Publicity Department, "Namna bora ya kuendesha Mikutano ya vyama." (Swahili).
  - Two form letters from C. P. Kapungu re formation of "Peoples Educational Movement," dated March 12 and April 5, 1962.
  - Tanganyika Plantation Workers Union, "Enquiry for Mass Dismissals of Workers in the Sisal Industry," May 17, 1963 (in Swahili)., Memo
  - TFL Educational Programme, June - August, 1962.
  - Three miscellaneous publications in Swahili.
  - Rules of National Union on Tanganyika Workers (Constitutions).
  - National Union of Tanganyika Workers
    - Speech by M. M. Kamaliza, General Secretary, National Union of Tanganyika Workers.
    - NUTA's Annual Congress, March 24-31, 1965, Dar-es-Salaam., (orig. handwritten copy & process-copy)
    - N.U.T.W. Hq. Taarifa ya Mwandishi Mkuu. 24th - 31st March, 1965.
  - Resolutions of First Annual Congress of NUTA, March 24-31, 1965, Dar-es-Salaam.
  - TFL Analytical Deck. Minutes of various meetings.
  - Codes for special TFL index deck.
  - TFL Trade Union badges (2).
Microfilms
- Tanganyika Standard, November 1, 1956 - August 10, 1959 (Reel 1)
- Sunday News, January - May 1959
- USIS Swahili Press Translations, August 1959 - July 1960
- Mirembe Hospital Annual Report, 1959
- Tanganyika Federation of Labour (TFL) (Reel 2)
  - Minutes of meetings
    - General council
    - Annual conferences
    - Emergency Committee
  - Correspondence
- East Africa, August 1963 (Reel 3)
- East Africa, August 1963 (Reel 4)
- Miscellaneous (Reel 5)